I came to Australia to study the deadliest animal in the world.
Now, there may be some Australian audience members thinking, Struth,
science has finally recognized the importance of the drop bears.
But I'm not studying drop bears because around the world, by
transmitting diseases like malaria and dengue fever, mosquitoes kill
more than a million people every year, making them the deadliest animal on the planet.
Now, in Australia, the most common mosquito borne disease is
Ross River virus and it occurs at high rates in some areas,
but not others. My question is why? What is it about certain
areas that makes them breed disease? If we can understand the
environmental factors that contribute to disease transmission, then we can alter
the environment or target our control efforts to prevent human infections.
But to answer that question, I had to find out where the
infected mosquitoes were in South Australia. And traditionally, testing mosquitoes
for virus has always been difficult. So I used a new technique.
It takes these cards, which are embedded with virus preserving chemicals,
and coats them in honey. Mosquitoes will come to feed on the
honey and in the process, spit virus onto the card where
it can later be detected. Now, no one had ever used
this technique in a broad scale virus survey before, so I had
to adapt it. I developed new traps and set them at over
a hundred field sites across South Australia. And I captured over 20,000
hungry mosquitoes and let them feed on the card for a week
before testing the cards for virus. Now you may not think that
these traps look very impressive, but science doesn't have to be beautiful.
It has to be effective. And these traps are proving to be
our most sensitive method of detecting infected mosquitoes. I found three types
of infection: Ross River virus, Barmah forest virus and Stratford virus
which has never before been found in South Australia. I now have
the virus data I need to conduct my analysis and I'm collecting
publicly available data about the environment surrounding my traps, like the
density of human housing, the biodiversity of mammals and the ratio
of green space to buildings, to see if any of those environmental
factors can link these virus hotspots that I've shown here.
But the most exciting part of my research so far has been the
success of this method. Public health officials in Victoria, Queensland and
Western Australia have been in contact with us about implementing this technique
for their surveillance next year. And I developed these traps on a tight budget.
I used recycled milk cartons, pantyhose and paper clips
to make the traps. Each trap costs less than a dollar and
can be reused for the whole season. That was important to me
because the majority of mosquito borne disease risk happens in economically
impoverished countries. In India, for example, where about a quarter of
the population lives on a dollar a day,
there are thirty three million cases of dengue infection every year. With my low budget virus
surveillance and spatial analysis method, I can help any country regardless
of resources find out where their deadliest animals occur, why they're there,
and how we can stop them from infecting humans. Thanks.